this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
sea radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
hello everyone welcome to this episode
of software engineering radio this is
your host content shrinky and our guest
today is Matt frisbee Matt has worked in
web development for over a decade he's
worked at Google dodash and has been a
startup co-founder as a Google software
engineer Matt worked on both the AdSense
and isolated mobile Pages platforms but
has very recently authored a book on
browser extensions which is our topic
today in addition to this book Matt has
ordered three others professional
JavaScript for web developers angular 2
cookbook and angularjs web application
development cookbook welcome to the show
math it's great to have you here is
there anything you'd like to add to your
bio before we get started with browser
extensions
I think that's good yeah I'm ready to
talk about the book excited to be on so
let's to start with water browser
extensions and can you give examples of
popular extensions and possibly key
Industries where extensions are most
popular sure so I say in the book that
browser extensions are strange and
Powerful parasites
I think that really captures the nature
of them
so they're these pieces of software that
are mostly written with standard web
technology and they sit on top of your
browser and they can do a lot of things
just about anything really the only
restriction is kind of the permissions
you give it and I describe in the book
they're kind of a hybrid of a website
and a mobile app and so from there you
really only limited by your imagination
because I think most software developers
don't truly appreciate how powerful this
software is you know there are some
limitations and we'll get into that in
the podcast but I think that they're
really underrated as a platform in
general
so major industries so according to
google almost half of chrome users have
at least one browser extension installed
and I would bet any amount of money that
the most popular extension is an ad
blocker because that's most people do
not want to see ads when they're
browsing the web and ad blockers are
extremely effective at that so that's by
far the most popular format but
obviously that's not a money maker does
tend to be free an open source software
but there are large companies that are
based off of primarily browser
extensions so the largest one that
people have heard of is probably honey
which is an extension that will
automatically well it does a lot of
things but the thing that is probably
best known for is it automatically looks
up and tries coupon codes when you're
shopping online and then to get you the
best discount and PayPal bought honey
for four billion dollars just a couple
years ago so you know honey outgrew the
browser extension platform but that was
still definitely its primary piece of
software so there are large companies
Loom is another great one I actually
know one of the co-founders of loom and
their extension is a screen recording
software that allows you to easily you
know generate you know instructional
recordings or whatever of a piece of
software and they have raised a ton of
money their eight figure valuation
they're a huge company a big piece of
their software platform is a browser
extension so these companies are out
there other categories like AI
assistance like grammarly is a big one
which you know watches you type and is
able to you know make Corrections and
suggestions password managers is a big
one so like you know LastPass although
their reputation is a little bit stained
lately and then there's also things like
developer tools so you know react is Far
and Away the most popular JavaScript
framework there are plenty of extensions
that are able to kind of plug into a
react project and then expose additional
information that's helpful to developers
inside the browser console so there's a
ton of different places that browser
extensions really Thrive and then there
are some up and coming areas that I'm
really excited about that we'll talk
about in the podcast so you mentioned
honey you said the starters as a browser
extension and you know now they have
some other mediums but starting as a
broader extension is useful because it's
right there where the user needs them
and that certainly sounds very useful
for react or any other Dev tools as well
so you talked about Chrome you use the
word browser extension so can you
develop the extension for One browser
and expect to be able to run it on all
others right so the landscape is a
little bit complicated right now
so no there's not a way to write it once
and have it work everywhere there are
certain platforms that are trying to get
closer to that but there are
idiosyncrasies that are unique to each
browser you know you have to do it
slightly differently
however the browser extensions have
pretty much coalesced around the web
extensions API which was the successor
to the mozilla's original
extension language was xol and XP com
which was a much more extensible and
somewhat argue a superior platform that
was able to customize almost anything
about the browser that has given way to
the modern web extensions API which is
has a smaller interface is still quite
powerful and then that's kind of the
meat of what extensions use to do what
they do so most browsers do support that
API but there are quirks that require
special considerations for each browser
so there's kind of levels of
compatibility that you can strive for so
personally you know if I'm just one
person working at an extension if I
publish an extension in the Chrome web
store which is by far the largest
platform automatically I can address
like 80 of desktop browsers because you
get Chrome right off the bat obviously
which is probably about two-thirds of
traffic and then you also get all the
browsers that are built off of the
chromium open source browser engine so
that gives you Opera that gives you edge
that gives you Brave there are some
others but just right there you're
addressing 80 of traffic and so that
generally can be a single code base so
that gets you pretty far where it gets
tricky Firefox which they're still
transitioning to manifest V3 which we'll
talk about later and then Safari which
is it's its own animal in and of itself
they have a kind of a wacky way of
deploying extensions but it's powerful
and pretty new so we're really the three
large buckets if you want to get as much
traffic as possible would be like Safari
Firefox those both require special
deployment and then kind of all chromium
extensions you can almost have a unified
code base so you mentioned manifest33
and we suddenly will dig into that but
it might make sense to just Define what
the Manifest file is at this point so
there's some context sure yeah so the
Manifest that's like the core piece of a
browser extension so when you browser
extensions loaded in the browser the
Manifest tells the browser kind of where
everything is what it's supposed to be
able to do some basic details like the
name and description icon and things
like that yeah it's a pretty simple file
but it's kind of the glue that holds
everything together
so manifest V3 is the latest iteration
of the Manifest
obviously it comes after manifest V2 and
the transition is kind of controversial
so the Manifest V3 push is being pushed
by Google pretty much exclusively it
started there and so the way it was
initially announced was that is oh it's
going to improve security oh it's going
to improve performance you know so we're
making all these changes but it's pretty
obvious that one of the main intentions
is to kind of start pushing people kind
of away from ad blockers so manifest V3
kind of wrapped into this transitional
period is a phasing out of the primary
API that powers ad blockers which is the
blocking web request API so the way that
all ad blockers work more or less is
that you can give an extension
permission to manage every individual
Network request going on on the browser
so it can see everything and more
importantly it can manage everything so
in ad blocker if it's installed give it
permissions with the blocking web
request API so if it sees an outgoing
request to you know double click which
is you know the Google ad server it can
go oh no that's I'm not going to serve
that request I'm going to block that and
the browser is very well equipped to go
okay you know where it's Network
requests fail all the time like we just
won't load that and so that's the meat
of how all ad blockers work there's
additional pieces of it but that's the
core piece that it's able to for any
individual Quest it can go in and zap
the request effectively and say I'm not
loading that manifest V3 kills that API
entirely or at least triples it in a
meaningful way and replaces it with an
entirely new API called the declarative
net request and the problem with that is
that for the blocking web request API
you're able to write a piece of
JavaScript that runs every time a
network request happens or matches a
regex or something like that and then
that JavaScript can be arbitrarily
complex so you can say oh you know if I
detect an ad request being sneaky I can
still you know sniff it out in all these
different ways but declarative net
request that API you're limited to this
like declarative style so you're
basically passing the browser a Json
file with all these static instructions
that say oh you know block requests to
this domain that look like this you know
that loads an image that loads
JavaScript it's still pretty
customizable but you're now basically
delegating the ad blocking to the
browser say all requests that match this
criteria block those and it sounds
similar but the important difference is
that you no longer have the ability to
intimately control what requests are
being killed in the browser and so very
powerful tool for ad blockers is not
quite as powerful anymore and so now
we're kind of hoping that basically the
browser vendors that you know maintain
the browser code bases Google continues
to allow the ad blockers to work and you
can see that there's a problem there
because they are you know they're 80 of
Google's revenues comes from ads and
they're also maintaining this platform
that's killing ads so these things are
completely in conflict with each other
and so this transition in manifest V3 it
seems very predictable that this was
going to happen eventually so it remains
to be seen what else is going to happen
with manifest V3 but it's problematic
because they're kind of watering down
what is the most probably the most
important ability of browser extensions
which is to moderate the traffic and out
of the browser that sounds really
interesting though I can imagine and
from what you said the we too and I'm
I'm hoping the V3 continues to be
powerful in terms of what the extensions
can do but also comes in with security
best practices because certainly when
there's too much that the extension can
do there's also a fear of
you know if you don't have the best
practices or you don't have the best
intentions that things could go wrong
and that could reduce the amount of
trust that customers have so maybe if
you can just delve into some security
best practices When developing
extensions and then we'll move on to our
next topic sure so security is in a
really interesting area of extensions
because you have to be cognizant of what
they have access to as well as what the
web page itself has access to because I
think it's kind of unusual to think when
you're writing JavaScript that runs in
the page that you have to think in an
adversarial way because probably the
biggest security hole that you know
browser extensions dance around is you
know the Dom is shared entity now so the
host webpage whatever it is let's say
you've written an extension for you know
a Gmail plug-in for example so Gmail is
rendering its own HTML their JavaScript
is running doing its thing
your extensions JavaScript is also
running in a separate container but
they're both talking to the same Dom so
anything that is being pulled out of the
Dom referenced in the Dom typed into the
Dom is visible to both so like for
example if you were to build like a
widget that is a Content script which is
a piece of JavaScript that runs in the
page that lets you render whatever you
want if you for example have a login
that sits in the page and someone types
in their username and password the host
page can see that username and password
and do whatever they want with it that
doesn't mean I'm not saying Gmail would
do that but whatever site you're doing
like they have the keys to the castle so
there are ways to protect against that
but kind of understanding where the
crossover points happen is really
important and I think the other part of
it is that I think I'll go ahead and
kind of kick around LastPass recently
because I'm a LastPass user and I was
going to change hundreds of passwords
last week which is a lot of fun the
amount of information that a properly
permissioned extension has access 2 is
quite profound so it's not a joke when
they say that if they have the proper
permissions they can see all your web
activity everything you type everything
the page everything all things they can
send requests on your behalf not saying
they do that all the top extensions are
very trustworthy and you know it's a
great place for open source to kind of
instill trust in the user but they have
access to everything and so extensions
like LastPass that are recording your
passwords presumably to keep them safe
they are accessing a lot of valuable
information and they have to be good
stewards of that information and any
extensions you build that have access to
support information it needs to be
protected because it really is you know
how much of our life is spent online if
it can sniff everything you're doing
that's a that's a really big attack
Vector so really being aware of like
what you're storing and where you're
putting it that's probably the biggest
security concern and the big LastPass
breach recently just kind of underscores
what can go wrong when you're not a good
Steward of death better so
what's the consumer to do how do we know
to trust an extension it's a good
question so there's really no one single
way of doing it so personally all the
extensions that I actively maintain
they're all open source so you can see
everything that's getting packaged into
the extension I find that that I mean
not a lot of people will take the time
to go through the code but it just being
there is kind of okay I can see what
you're doing and so there's a certain
level of trust that that instills so the
way that extensions display permission
messages some people have problems with
it because it's a little bit aggressive
and it is so like for example the tabs
permission which is a very common
permission to request so you can you
know open new tabs close tabs move them
around whatever it is I think the Chrome
permission for that will say can view
your entire browsing history and
something else something very scary
sounding so I think one big thing is pay
attention to what the permission warning
messages are telling you because that's
really the last line of defense that's
like if it's saying it can see all your
browsing history and you know read all
your web pages whatever the message is
like that's real if an untrusted person
gets access to this extension they
really can see everything and cause a
lot of problems and the reason I bring
this up is that it's pretty common for
extensions to be purchased or people to
attempt to purchase them just to get
access to the users and permissions so
for example I launched a chat GPT
extension recently and it got a bunch of
users right away because I was pretty
early out of the gate and I had people
contacting me looking to acquire the
extension I don't know what they were
going to do with it I didn't say yes to
any of them but I don't think their
intentions were good because I think
it's a pretty common pattern for someone
to come swoop in buy an extension
do bad things with it and then kind of
move on to the next one because they are
this kind of asymmetric model that like
if you pay a couple thousand bucks to
get an extension with you know 20 000
users and you have access to all their
web browsing activity that's a problem
and that definitely goes on I would hope
not too often but those people are out
there so yeah pay attention to the
warning messages and stick to Professor
the extensions so yeah I mean you know
stick to the bigger ones and I maybe
don't be too adventurous
so later in the show I think we should
spend a little bit of time giving this
on how the developer can create more
trust as well let's move into the
architecture now for a little bit
so might be useful to start with just
the very basics of how the browser
renders the web page and then the key
elements of how extensions fit in there
sure so the architecture is probably one
of the more confusing aspects to people
that are new to developing extensions
because outside of the Manifest file
there's really no aspect that's required
for any given extension and on top of
that there's really no primary user
interface with which you can interact
with whatever the extension is doing so
there's some big pieces that are common
there's like the pop-up which is an
interface that you can open when you
know someone either clicks the toolbar
icon or you can also trigger with a
hotkey there's the options page which is
this like you know a standalone web page
that the URL the host is like on Chrome
it's like Chrome extension colon slash
slash and then the path to wherever the
file is there's content scripts which is
probably one of the more extensible and
customizable aspects where you can
inject JavaScript and CSS into the page
and then do all sorts of interesting
stuff with it there's the developer
tools interface which you can add custom
Pages like right into the browser's
developer tools that have access to the
special subset of apis and then there's
the well in manifest V3 it's a service
worker there's a background script
that's it's a service worker so it's
event driven and then that's like the
piece of JavaScript that's like
listening to browser events and open
push to storage and you know do all
sorts of stuff that's the piece that
sort of ties all of the disparate
elements together and so it's a really
bizarre stack so the extension itself
functions as like kind of a file server
so if like let's say You're Building it
with uh like you're building like a
react app for your options page you know
all the requests for static files things
like that are like they're being
directed towards the extension and it's
able to like serve these files into you
know an options page or like you can so
you can serve files directly into the
web page itself for a Content script so
it's kind of this constellation of
different pieces and different
extensions will use whatever is the most
appropriate so like honey for example
they'll paint stuff into the page like a
little widget for showing when it's
trying to inject coupon codes or
LastPass when using it because all the
stuff needs to be protected it can't put
it can't put your passwords in the page
so that lives inside the pop-up because
only the extension exact has access to
the pop-up or react developer tools they
will there's really no user interface
outside of the developer tools itself
because that's the place that kind of
makes the most sense because when you're
building a website and using react
that's where you're spending a ton of
time inside the developer tools so yeah
it's just a bunch of these pieces that
can be assembled in different ways and
can you kind of use what you need and
don't use what you don't need
so the pop-up is where the user has to
take an explicit action to invoke the
extension is that correct right so the
pop-up is probably the interface that
most people are familiar with so there's
right when you install an extension
you'll get inside like the extension bar
on desktop at least you'll get a little
extra icon that you can you know as a
clickable Target and so most people you
know are not tech savvy or whatever this
is going to be the most comfortable
experience for them because it's a
visible button they can see it they can
click on it they can right click on it
and do different things but the
interface of click the button get the
the pop-up window that's most people are
very comfortable with doing that and so
most extensions should at least have
something there when you click that
because people are definitely expecting
it but what I understood is honey used
the content script which automatically
changed the page in some way that the
user would recognize but the user would
not have necessary to take any action to
have that is that correct precisely so
the biggest problem with content scripts
or it's not a problem it's by Design is
that you can't programmatically open
them so if you want to kick open a small
window to show
a settings page or a login or whatever
it is there's no event that can open the
pop-up script other than something that
the user directly does so it's either
you're either clicking the icon itself
or you're doing a hotkey to open the
pop-up but you can't like you can't call
a piece of JavaScript to open the pop-up
it doesn't work that way so a lot of
popular extensions will emulate that so
sometimes they'll like kind of do a
Content strip widget in a similar spot
to where the pop-up would open to kind
of make it feel more familiar because
that you can open up programmatically
but of course you're not getting the
sandbox safety of the pop-up script but
yeah so like honey it needs to talk to
the page and it's not handling any
sensitive information because of the
coupon codes like who cares so all the
widgets in the page they'll just stick
right in there because that you know you
can control that programmatically and
there's no restriction on when you can
show it so content scripts are
definitely more user friendly because
there's just more you can do with them
and then you talked about the service
worker which is a background skip so I
assume there needs to be some kind of
communication between the background
script and content script
right so the communication medium for
extensions is messaging so one of a
couple different types of messaging but
it's all it's basically the same concept
as a post message that you know it's
this asynchronous messaging and you know
you can open a channel it can just be a
one-off messaging it's bi-directional so
you can send a response multiple tabs
can talk to the service worker at once
you know extensions can talk to each
other there's also ways for extensions
to talk to Native software it's all done
via message passing because the
different pieces they will have
different exposure to the apis so for
example like a Content script doesn't
have access like it can't handle
extension events but it can send
messages to the background which thereby
can handle those events so the
background will be able to exchange
messages with the content script
exchange messages with a pop-up exchange
messages with the options page and the
background or sorry excuse me the
developer tools and so it's kind of
acting as the hub for the extension
itself the service worker is also useful
in this case because that's the it's
guaranteed to be a Singleton so there's
only ever going to be one service worker
for any given extension and so that's
very useful because if you're tying
together a bunch of these different UI
pieces that you know have all these
different considerations the service
worker you can always kind of fall back
on that I mean there's only only give me
one handing handling message in this way
and that kind of makes it easier to tie
everything together so we've talked
about permissions and in the context of
a security mechanism as well
what are permissions and what are the
different kind of permissions and how
does the author requests permissions
permissions are tricky because I devoted
a whole chapter to them at some level
they expect pretty much how you'd think
that if you want to do something that
requires any elevated
permission you request the corresponding
permission so for example like there's
an alarms API so you can like have a
piece of code run in the background like
every minute for example so that's
called an alarm so you request the
alarms API if you want to talk to a
certain domain so like let's say I
wanted to send requests to google.com I
can request a host permission and I
would say okay give me you know I just
Define a regex that gives me the ability
to talk to google.com from the extension
and there's I don't know like a hundred
different permissions that you can
request some of which are will trigger a
warning message and some of which will
not so like for example the alarms API
it's not really doing anything sensitive
when you submit to the Chrome web store
you will need to say like here's what
it's for and you put in like a sentence
but the user is never going to see a
pop-up because that's not there's no
opportunity for abuse really whereas if
you're requesting access to every you
know that tabs API or you're requesting
the all urls host permission which gives
you the access to everything they're
going to get a pop-up that says you know
the extension you know either on update
or when it's installed saying the
extension is requesting all this stuff
you know is that okay and so a useful
pattern if you don't want to scare the
user because they some of the warning
messages can be very scary are optional
permissions so basically you can have
when they initially install it you can
have the core subset of permissions that
your extension requires to work and
those will be applied automatically and
then if you want to have them you know
on a one-off basis Grant additional
permissions you can do that you can you
know it will still incur the warning
window for permissions that are more
sensitive but they will they will be
explicitly requesting them so it won't
be as scary as like getting all these
warning messages on install one caveat
with permissions which is a pretty ugly
aspect of extension development in my
submission is that if you add required
permissions to an extension and then
push that out in an update everyone who
has it installed will have to reapprove
the extension which is depending on how
much they need the extension can have a
substantial amount of attrition so your
browser will disable it like in Chrome
you know if you have extensions
installed you've probably seen this
before there's like a little yellow
exclamation point in the settings menu
and you'll have to explicitly re-enable
the extension that's requested a
sensitive permission and a lot of
developers will get bit by this when
they're not expecting it because it's a
really unpleasant user flow so if you're
trying to avoid things like that
optional permissions are your friend so
permissions is a key mechanism
and you know there may be concerns in
how some of these are displayed to the
user but other other mechanisms in the
browser to prevent any extension
vulnerabilities
yeah so I manifest V3 went pretty far to
address some of these so one of the
biggest things that was taken away was
the ability to execute arbitrary scripts
so that's been taken away and it's
unclear so there are extensions like
they're called user script instentions
and so the idea is that in manifest V2
you would be able to install an
extension there's one called Grease
Monkey there's one called tampermonkey
they're pretty popular that you can
basically Define your own JavaScript
that has access to the extension apis
that you can do whatever you want run it
whenever you want about as extensible as
it can get and basically that would be
you know calling the JavaScript eval
function and then that's what's running
your JavaScript or some equivalent of it
but you basically you can inject
arbitrary JavaScript and in this case
the user wants it manifest V3 does away
with that entirely presumably to you
know deal with cross-site scripting
because that's a pretty sensitive thing
so in manifest 3 all the JavaScript that
runs has to come from the package
extension so you can't load a third
party script from like a remote website
you can't like type in JavaScript and
have it run that none of that's allowed
anymore with the extension of you can
run it in a sandbox but that's less
useful and so all these problems kind of
go away to a certain extent when you
take away this ability to run
third-party JavaScript but at the same
time it's you know it's problematic
because you're inherently disabling
these really useful extensions that a
lot of people find useful I spent some
time on the extension specific apis so
you introduced these earlier on
can you describe the scope of what can
be done with access to these apis
sure so there's common ones you know
storage is a really common one so you
can request different types of storage
that are
separated from the web page itself so
it's an asynchronous storage you know
you can request different amounts of
space so there's like an unlimited
storage permission on you can store as
much stuff as you want which is useful
if you know if your extension is like
recording video or stuff like that yeah
so there's I mean apis for
authentication so one kind of tricky
corner of extensions is like how do you
authenticate someone and so there's this
whole set of like oauth especially
like how do you deal with like
authenticating a person with the oauth
protocol which is particularly difficult
because you need these callback URLs and
so browser extensions have a native way
of dealing with these things but it's
kind of it's kind of tricky to do
because these oauth has kind of built
around being used in like a website
format and so yeah there's a whole API
to deal with like oauth and extension
yeah like what I mean I talked about the
messaging there's a ton of like apis to
deal with like the browser Chrome itself
so there's an omnibox API which allows
you to like kind of show autocomplete
search results like from the browser bar
there's like a context menu API so like
when you right click like you can add an
entire right-click menu That's sensitive
to like what you're clicking on the page
there's a ton of apis dealing with like
Network requests themselves so like you
can
you know you can sniff like what's being
loaded on the page what is the browsing
history things like that there's like a
pairs of bookmarks API so you can manage
the person's bookmarks the tabs API
talked about so you have total control
over what tabs are being opened closed
pinned muted whatever it is yeah there's
a there's the list goes on and on but
it's pretty extensive what they can do
and I it's not really that much of an
exaggeration to say that pretty much
anything that you can do in the browser
an extension can do for you to a certain
extent so can we talk about some of the
key differences across browsers
that you know of in support of these
apis yeah so browsers have mostly
coalesced around the web extensions API
so that core set of apis is pretty well
supported where there's some
fragmentation are on so for example
Mozilla is planning on continuing its
support for the blocking web request API
even though like next week they're about
to roll out support for manifest V3 so
that fragmentation is it's interesting
we'll see where it goes because now
Firefox is becoming the only major
platform that will be supporting the
blocking WebQuest API that all ad
blockers need Firefox also has like a
whole bunch of extra like themes and
things like that they have their own bag
of apis that are you know unique to that
platform there's some idiosyncrasies
with how the different apis behave on
platforms but there's not a ton so if
you're I mean if you're within the core
web extensions API everything you know
any major browser vendor has pretty
nicely come in and supported the web
extensions API so development is pretty
nice in that respect
that's good to no sense that certainly
reduces the amount of work you would
have to do to have your extension work
across browsers moving on to a little
bit of detail now on pop-up Pages
content scripts and background Scripts
so starting with the content scripts and
maybe pop-up pages how much control does
the developer have on The Styling and
especially I think that's relevant in
the case of content script because you
are updating the existing web page
so what should you keep in mind as you
start to style the user interface of the
extension and any caveats there
yeah so content scripts are an
interesting one so pop-up pages and
options Pages those are behave pretty
much as you would expect so you know
it's a web page that you're exclusively
rendering there's no CSS bleed or
anything like that so what you see is
what you get for those pages and so
that's really useful because that's you
know it's more akin to a traditional web
development environment where it's it's
basically rendering like a website
content scripts are a different animal
right so in the Manifest you're defining
pieces of you know JavaScript files and
CSS files that are being injected into
the page and you get to you know Define
when they're injected and then if
there's a domain match like whether or
not a piece of JavaScript or css should
be injected but after that that's you
know the JavaScript kind of is on its
own and so you have to sort of bootstrap
the user interface you know just using
these pieces of JavaScript and so
there's some interesting considerations
obviously one is CSS bleed so the ideal
pattern that I actually can't take
credit for this this is the plasmo guys
who wrote the forward for the book they
were the first ones that came up with
this that I saw was basically if you
want to put a widget in the page but you
want to protect it from CSS you put it
inside of Shadow Dom so you'll have the
JavaScript will render whatever your
widget looks like inside a shadow Dom
and then you can have the CSS be
injected inside that shadow Dom so it
doesn't affect the parent page and then
it's restricted to Only The Shadow on
itself and so that's a really useful
pattern because now you can style stuff
the way you want to and you don't have
to worry about messing up the parent
page which is pretty problematic and
that's kind of a big pain point or that
was a big pain point until I started
folding Shadow Dom into all my
extensions so good job plasma guys on
that one yeah but then as I mentioned
before the content script then how it
folds into the page is really up to you
so there are some contexts where you'll
want to integrate more tightly so if
you're so a lot of like Gmail extensions
well the developers will ahead of time
they kind of know what the Dom looks
like inside Gmail and so they can go oh
I can look for this certain pattern of
you know pieces of the Dom and then I
can inject my own button in there and
then it will look like a piece of the
Native Don and so then if I can style it
however I want and I can have it trigger
whatever interfaces I want but it's
going to be stuck inside the page so
it'll look like a piece of Gmail
other ones will like pop over the page
so for example if you're like a LastPass
user you'll notice that LastPass will
stick a little LastPass icon over the
end of an input element and if you click
that it'll pop a widget over the page
that's pretty common pattern because
it's you know it's pretty cheap and easy
to to locate like a small box widget
over the page and then there's also
extensions that will kind of have like a
floating button in the bottom right of
the page that will trigger something
more substantial kind of like a pop over
like a modal window that's pretty common
content script pattern yeah so content
scripts are they're really they have to
be judiciously applied because like you
can totally mangle the host page or the
host page will mangle your content
script so you have to be very careful
with yeah how it's being applied in the
page but at the same time it's the most
natural way to like extend and interact
with the host page and it really allows
for the most powerful stuff so you
mentioned that the mangling can happen
in both directions
and one of the key user experience
elements was having a floating element
on top which I assume will be helpful
with the CSS property Z index so are
there any best practices around using
that property so it really depends on
what the host page looks like so there
are certain pages where it makes sense
to just you know use the Z index to kind
of just force your widget on top of
everything but then you have to be you
know you have to be sensitive about you
know is the host page also going to use
the index to push stuff on top and am I
going to interfere with that because
that's right so Z index that's one of
the few CSS properties that that's going
to cause problems right because you're
setting the Z index presumably on the
shadow Dom host element itself so you
could be pulling your extension on top
of everything and then the user is going
to be like what's going on I can't see
anything or vice versa the host page is
going to be covering up your stuff and
make your extension unusable so in any
event it really requires if you're going
the content script route you have to be
very sensitive towards what is actually
going on on the page because that's
really going to drive how you're
integrating with the host platform so
like for example a server side rendered
website will be much easier to integrate
with because you know that you know if
it's just sending you back a blob of
HTML you know you can modify that
without fear of like a single page
application you know blowing it up or I
mean at least it's less likely whereas
if you're integrating with this like
really involved react app you know it
could be re-rendering all the time and
the URLs might look the same
and you have to be aware of like is the
host page going to wipe out my content
script entirely so all these things are
kind of under the same umbrella of
really having a good understanding of
what your host page is doing and can do
that will
make it play nicely with whatever your
extension is trying to do besides the
mechanism you mentioned using Shadow Dom
can iframes be used as well to isolate
styling they can I don't recommend it
it's all the benefits of using an iframe
so the problem with iframes is if you're
putting it on a host page you're subject
to the same origin restrictions as the
host page so you can't the host page you
know if you're trying to load an iframe
from you know whatever the host website
is of the extension you know if you're
sticking an iframe in the page the host
page it may zap that outcome request and
say yeah you can't I'm not letting you
embed that domain and so at that point
the
sandboxing abilities of an iframe
they're harder to work with and they're
a little bit more finicky than a shadow
Dom and Shadow Dom supported pretty much
everywhere so I would say it was pretty
rare where the use case of an iframe
exceeds the utility and kind of
flexibility of just a you know a vanilla
Shadow Dom post and you certainly don't
have a lot of this complexities if you
use a pop-up page but it's not as well
integrated with the page that you're
accessing so there's some trade-offs
there right right yeah what about the
use of JavaScript Frameworks or
libraries to write these extensions yeah
so this is the place where JavaScript
Frameworks really shine so as I
mentioned before the pop-up and options
pages are working off of the what's
essentially a simple file server that
the extension is behaving as and so if
you want to have like an options page
for example so the URL for the options
page can be something like you know
Chrome extension colon slash you know
your extension ID slash options.html and
that's going to send a get request for
that actual file inside the extension
file server now if you want to have a
really complicated let's say you're
doing a react app there let's say you
want routing well there's no ability to
handle a traditional server-side routing
so I've found that doing like a hash
routing solution is more useful there
because obviously you know the hash part
of the URLs is not affecting the path to
the actual file file and so this is
where single page applications really
shine because you can now have a fully
fledged web page that you know has
routing and you know can support you
know going back and forth and things
like that but it's still living off of
the same file and there's really not a
alternate way of doing that unless
you're having separate you know HTML
files for each interface and that's just
not as good of an experience as a single
page app and the other part of it is
that because it's basically a local file
server it can load everything really
quickly so considerations like you know
large static assets or you know loading
things from the server like you know
these things are still important and you
don't want to you know load 10 megabytes
at JavaScript for you know like a
one-page file but
everything's going to load basically
instantly because it's loading off your
local file system instead of some remote
server so these things make you know
extensions can be a pretty Snappy
interface just because you know
everything's local and you know
everything is running off of the same
box thanks for that Matt I wanted to
cover some other key topics that we've
mentioned in our talk but not
necessarily in sufficient details
so let's start with the dev tools pages
I think you mentioned that in the
context of helping Developers
implementing react
so can you just give a little bit of
what the use case would be what does an
example of an extension
here in this area sure well the two that
I use frequently are just react
developer tools and then there's a Redux
react Redux extension as well and so the
premise is relatively simple basically
the extension is able to create custom
panels inside the browser's developer
tools and it's pretty similar to an
options page or a pop-up page that you
can render it however you like but it
also gets access to a few special
browser apis so it can really tightly
understand what the Dom structure is
like you can inject pieces you know
scripts into the page to locate elements
or you know simple little script
injections you can sniff web traffic in
a really rich way and so typically the
way these are used is that like the
react developer tools extension can tell
if the web page is running a react app
and then there are different you know
there's different ways to kind of make
them play with each other so you can
have it be like oh yeah like the you
know your react app is rendering this
way and you know these components are
working this way and you know props and
so forth are filtering down so it's
especially useful for kind of debugging
and understanding what's going on with
single page applications because they
can intimately integrate with
what's going on on the page understand
it and then show it in developer tools
and in ways that you know you can you
know interact and understand kind of
what's going on behind the scenes and so
I would most all major single page
applications have some sort of developer
tools like companion extension like this
since it does prove to be so useful in
so many cases
okay makes sense so we did chat about
manifest V2 versus V3 to some extent you
know you said the key difference was it
might make it harder likely will make it
harder to implement ad blockers what
else is different than what else is the
challenge of migrating from B2 to V3
yeah so this is a big pain point for
certain extensions so most extensions
will find that the the transition is
pretty painless but there are a few
types of extension that are their future
looks pretty bleak so you're right so
off the top of my head so we've talked
about user script extensions so
tampermonkey and grease monkey so the
ability to run custom JavaScript is
getting thrown out the window the Chrome
team has said that they're looking into
ways to continue to allow these because
these extensions have millions of
installs so it remains we've seen what's
happening with those but those are last
I checked there was no path forward for
those although the Chrome team doesn't
indicated they want to save them other
ones are so the service worker has some
interesting introduces some interesting
problems so previously in manifest V2
the background was a headless web page
kind of and so you would have access to
the Dom and Dom apis and so a certain
extension would use those for
authentication audio apis things like
that and so now that it's a service
worker there's no Dom anymore right it's
the service worker global object and so
there's things like JS Dom that lets you
kind of emulate a Dom or there's like
the off-screen canvas API which lets you
recapture some of this Behavior but
taking with a Dom has been a big
headache for a lot of extensions so some
of the workarounds are keeping it
designated like a tab open all the time
like just have a supplementary HTML tab
open all the time and then use that Dom
that's not a solution though because
that's I right the user has now this
extra tab floating around all the time
just so you can have access to the Dom
it's a bad solution so it's not clear
what's going to happen with those
extensions they also might be in trouble
and then one big one is the life cycle
of the service worker itself so there
are some extensions that like let's say
you wanted to open a websocket a Long
Live websocket or something that needs
to run for an extended period of time
Chrome will aggressively shut down a
service worker as because it's a service
worker and it's designed to be you know
this quickly destroyable restartable
thing and so any extension that needs a
background script to run persistently no
longer has the ability to do so because
the Chrome will shut it down after I
think five minutes is the typical
timeout so there are hacks that can
prolong the life cycle of the service
worker but any extensions that need a
long-running background script there's
no path forward for those either and all
these problems I mentioned the Chrome
team has indicated they what they want
to address them and has said that for a
long time but it seems to be progressing
slowly and at the same time it seems
like so I'll put it this way it seems
like the Chrome team cares because they
had initially set a rollout date of this
month actually January 2023 was that was
the hard stop date for I think it was
all manifest V2 extensions in the Chrome
web store would go dark and you know it
would they've already cut off V2
submissions but the existing published
V2 extensions could still be updated and
would still be public they have pushed
that back to I think in the middle of
2023 so June or something
because they know that they're not ready
and all these extensions that are
extremely popular are going to be killed
if they turn them off so
it seems to me the Chrome team cares
about you know preserving these
extensions that are kind of getting
crushed by manifest V3 but I don't
really know what's going to happen
because it doesn't seem like there's
much of a plan and I don't know they
haven't rammed it through yet but like
it would not surprise me if it got to
that point they just said well you'll
have to figure it out so yeah
installation man of sp3 is pretty
controversial and it remains to be seen
what's going to happen but if you're
writing a new extension you should start
with V3 at this point yes unless you're
really you know people are still writing
you V2 extensions because you know
they're targeting Firefox or you know
they really want to hang on to the old
apis but you know if you want to use the
Chrome web store if you want to have the
most users V2 is dead time to go for V3
so I did read about a safari web
extension converter do you have any
experience using that yeah so this was I
made sure to cover this in the book so
this is a really interesting development
so I think it was uh let's say two years
ago Safari or apple roll rolled out
extension support for Safari and so
traditionally extensions have not been a
mobile platform so Google obviously has
never rolled out extension support for
mobile Chrome I think everyone kind of
understands why they didn't do that
because they don't want to lose the ad
Revenue because it would be you know
billions of dollars out the window if
they did that so I think they just said
yeah we're not doing extensions for
mobile you know too bad so there are
ways to get extensions on mobile Firefox
is one way but you know there's a kiwi
browser for Android so you can do it on
an Android phone but there's really no
like first class support from like the
primary browser vendors until Safari
rolled out extension support so it's
pretty far away from how you would
typically develop extensions so
extensions have been you know HTML CSS
and JavaScript it's basically just
bundled together and then shoved into
the browser and the browser understands
what to do with it in Safari it's
packaged kind of like an app it does
function it's essentially as an
extension in the browser so if I wanted
to publish an extension for Safari I'd
build it inside xcode I'd have to get an
Apple developer account and I would
publish it on the app store and then
once it's installed like on your phone
for example you'll see it installed as
kind of an app and when you dive into
the code it's pretty interesting because
all the same extension pieces are there
so you still have a manifest you still
have content scripts and you know all
the files still work the same but
there's this kind of wrapper for the app
and so the wrapper itself is a mobile
app for Safari and you can talk to it
with the Native Messaging API so there's
this entirely extra piece of software
that's running on the phone that's it's
a Safari app I'm not a safari developer
but it it's I mean it's you can see it
on the device and you can like write
code for it to behave as an app so it's
this whole extra piece that lets you
kind of talk to the phone itself so the
Safari aspect of it is interesting for
that reason why because it's kind of
this new domain but it's also the first
major
4A into extensions for phones because
you know the iPhone is by far the most
popular phone and Safari is you know has
is a huge chunk of users being able to
run an extension admittedly inside a
Walled Garden is still pretty exciting
and it's really the hats off to Apple
for doing that because it seems like
Chrome the Google team was just never
going to do it for mobile and mobile
Computing is more than half of web
traffic these days and it's kind of
silly that you know there's that we're
not able to use into mobile devices so
good job Apple for supporting that and
so it's still kind of a clunky interface
so developing forward is kind of is kind
of difficult and not nearly as easy as
publishing to the Chrome web store but
it is certainly a promising future in
the context of browser extensions so not
as easy as a Chrome web store so what is
the approval process do you have a
separate one for each browser yeah so
each browser has its own
store so you know the Chrome web store
that's for Chrome although caveat on
that is that you other chromium browsers
can install from the Chrome web store
but Edge has its own Edge extension
store Opera has its own store Mozilla
has its own store yeah so you have to if
you want to appear in these stores you
have to submit you know your bundled
extension to each of these and there's a
separate approval process
so I'll say that it's a pain for sure
the plasma guys who wrote the forward
they have a pipeline that allows you to
automatically deploy to all the stores
which is really awesome and I suggest
anyone who has to deploy to all the
stores it's quite something and they've
put a lot of work into making it great
but it's you know you can also do it
just like one off so if you know if you
just want to publish in the Chrome web
store you know there's an API you can do
it through or you can just upload a zip
file that's you know the zip file is
pretty low overhead and then yeah
there's uh I should say it depends on
what your extension has asked for so if
it's a low permission extension that
doesn't ask for anything sensitive I
will typically see my extension like go
live in under 30 minutes so it seems
like that's an automated approval
Pipeline and they Google has some
automated process that they go okay yeah
that's probably not stealing anything so
you know we can just publish it go right
ahead so like the book has a companion
extension called example Chrome
extension that well because it has to
demo all the apis you know the extension
request basically every API imaginable
so whenever I submit updates to that
extension it takes days because
obviously someone has to like sit down
and look at it and be like okay why are
they asking for all the permissions in
the world and then you know then it gets
published in the same way but that takes
much much longer so I think the approval
process is pretty straightforward I
think it's just developers need to
understand like if you're requesting
certain extensions it takes like
50 times longer for the approval to go
through which can be pretty annoying I
spent a little bit of time maybe a
couple of minutes on testing and
monitoring is there anything unique to
testing extensions you know or is it
similar to how you would test any other
web application yeah so testing is
tricky so a lot of it's pretty manual so
one interesting thing with manifest P3
is that for modern web developers pretty
much every build tool offers a hot
module reload feature right so it can
quickly swap out pieces of the
application that were updated there's no
reload required and it can show it to
immediately which is
amazing when when you're writing code
and don't refresh the page every time
the problem is that this bumps up
against what manifest V3 allows for so
and depending on what piece so like if
you're writing a Content script for
example and you're writing a let's say
you've written a react widget to be
injected into the page the hot module
reload
can't reload just that thing so it's not
compatible there so you have to do a
page reload and at the same time you
also have to be careful about when you
need an extension reload so like when
you're going to kick out the service
worker and replace it with the updated
one and so there's a whole bunch of pain
points when you're doing this so for
example if you're one thing that I still
bites me in the butt to this day is that
if you're inspecting the service worker
when in development if you leave the
inspector window open it will keep the
service worker alive even after you
reload it and so all these really weird
bugs like come out of the wind you're
like what is going on and so it's just
the browser it's like okay I gotta keep
this alive because you saw the inspector
window open and so yeah so testing
extensions is kind of hard because it's
living in this weird like browser space
and then all the traditional you know
build tools are kind of geared towards
web development so some things translate
but yeah it's still a manual process and
there are still all these Kinks that may
or may not be worked out as for
monitoring extensions I would actually
say it's a superior experience to
monitoring web apps and the reason for
that is for the same reason that
extensions is so popular because ad
blockers for web page and ad blocker
eats like half of your analytics traffic
so for example you know if you stick
Google analytics on a page a number of
people using your web app I usually you
know you pay added by like 30 or 40
percent because those requests are
getting killed by ad blockers you will
never know that those people are viewing
your web page however if you are
installing analytics inside an extension
other ad blockers can't block net
requests from your extension so if
you're sending analytics from the
service worker you're going to get
perfect Fidelity for your analytics
which is great like being able to see
100 of the user activity and not have to
worry about ad blockers eating all your
stuff that's great so monitoring I would
say is actually nicer than web pages
because you're not losing all that
analytics data to ad blockers eating
your lunch
time to wrap up now so you did talk
about the plasma
platform
I think this was built by Stephen alexik
and Lewis we will go I hope I'm
pronouncing their names correctly who
wrote the forward to your book and you
talked about a use case where the
platform does help why for the approval
process across browsers how else do
these platforms help yeah the plasma
guys they've gone a really interesting
Direction so they've kind of built this
declarative model so when you're
building an extension instead of kind of
explicitly labeling everything out
inside a manifest file a lot of the
boilerplate stuff gets generated for you
so they've
figured out like a good way of injecting
you know one or multiple content scripts
they figure out a good way of managing
permissions and messaging and things
like that and so they've built it into
this kind of opinionated platform
but you get all these benefits once you
use the platform so
they have a really really nice command
line interface as I mentioned they've
got the store deployment
pipeline that's great yeah they're
actively working on it they're great
guys there's a lot of fun to talk to
them and so
I think they're really on to something
so there aren't a ton of platforms and a
lot of people home roll stuff but for
anyone who's looking to like find a
platform to easily get started like look
no further plasma like those guys are
those guys are killing it right now
and they have you know they're working
on some really important stuff and
they're really advancing sophisticated
extension development tools and boy Lord
knows we need those because this space
is uh it's still kind of the Wild West
it certainly is I couldn't find a lot of
material besides the official
documentations and then I chances in the
book
so we'll definitely have a link to the
book in our show notes okay how else can
people contact you yeah so Twitter's a
good way my Twitter handle is Matt frizz
yeah so building browser extensions.com
is the website for the book
you'll be able to buy the book there
there's contact info for me yeah you can
find me on LinkedIn there's a number of
ways to reach me uh or just Google my
name my personal site is Matt frizz.com
you can find my contact information
there so
yeah pretty reachable so certainly a
very interesting conversation Matt we've
got a lot of topics is there anything
else you think we should talk about
today with respect to browser extensions
so there is one thing and that is kind
of where the future is for browser
extensions
so I'm sure you're familiar with chat
GPT which was released in December and
has taken the World by storm and I think
that there's a really interesting
pairing between AI tools especially
lom's like chat GPT and things like
extensions so I wrote a blog post about
this but there has been an explosion of
browser extensions that use tools like
chat gbt and other you know open AI apis
to do cool things inside the browser and
so a lot of the ones have come up will
like can write emails for you and can
like summarize articles and you know
there's hundreds of extensions now that
utilize you know these language models
in some interesting way and the pairing
is really opens up some interesting
possibilities because like if you think
about what a web page actually is right
it's this hypertext you know it's a
pretty consistent length you know at
most a few thousand words usually images
and things like that and the inputs to
these large language models can handle
that amount of text and so there's this
new space where these AI tools can like
really richly understand like what
you're looking at and can you know
unpack all these things so they can
summarize what you're looking at or they
can you know have this conversational
understanding of like what your browsing
is and so there are certainly privacy
implications of like you know do I want
to be feeding you know this closed
Source AI model what I'm looking at but
browser extensions can what I really see
them as is like it's almost like a it's
a glimpse into like the future of
augment in reality because it's you know
they're adding these contextually useful
interfaces where you need them so
because it can so richly understand what
the page is showing it's able to go oh
you could really use you know a little
widget here that does you know XYZ or oh
you know we should really you know we
should format the page in this
interesting way because this will help
you know with XYZ so because an
extension can richly modify and
understand the page and because llms are
able to quickly ingest the contents of
the page and do useful things with them
there's this really interesting future
where browser extensions are kind of
this assistant that are you know kind of
modulating the way that we use the web
you know obviously so much of what we do
is now you know inside a web browser or
some Computing devices some form and so
having this layer over what we're
looking at that is a smart layer and is
able to you know modify and suggest
things really opens up some interesting
possibilities so I'm really excited
about the future of this pairing between
browser extensions and things like chat
GPT maybe it won't be the form of
necessarily like a browser extension
because you know they're mostly limited
to desktop browsers and that's you know
that's really only half a web browsing
but the ability to you know have this
controlled layer that's like this
assistant and can understand what you're
looking at and what you're doing it
gives a small glimpse into the future of
computing and it really excites me in a
profound way I did notice your article
on LinkedIn will definitely have these
links in the show notes this is a very
interesting conversation Matt thanks for
coming on to the show and I'm happy we
could have this conversation it's an
unusual space and I was happy to be on
to talk about it thanks all for
listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
foreign